"The Best Time to Workout
for Weight Loss"
What is the optimal exercise
timing for weight loss?
Is it better to exercise
in the morning or the evening?
Before breakfast
or after breakfast?
There was a Nobel Prize-
winning exercise physiologist
who said he always ran a mile
every morning before breakfast.
Was he right? Let’s find out.
More than a dozen experiments
have been published
comparing the amount
of fat burned
in a fasted versus fed state,
and every single one
found more fat was burned
on an empty stomach.
On average, a single bout of low-
to-moderate intensity activity
before a meal burned off
three grams more fat
than the same amount
of exercise after a meal.
That’s about three-quarters
of a pat of butter’s worth of fat,
enough to improve
insulin sensitivity.
The same amount of exercise,
but more fat loss,
all because of timing.
Now, just because you burn
more fat while you’re exercising
doesn’t necessarily
mean you end up
with less fat
at the end of the day.
Maybe your body offsets
the extra fat loss
that occurs during exercise
with a little extra fat storage
when you finally do eat,
balancing it out.
Researchers in Japan set out
to investigate the possibility
that your body makes
up for it later
by measuring 24-hour fat
balance after 100 minutes
of running either before
breakfast or after lunch.
On the exercise-after-lunch day,
they burned a total
of 608 calories of fat
over the course of that day.
In contrast, on the exercise-
before-breakfast days,
in the same 24-hour period
they burned through
nearly 90 percent more,
1,142 calories of straight fat.
So, the next day, they woke up
with about a quarter
cup of fat less
after the same amount
of exercise.
That’s remarkable!
What about just
something like walking?
Sixty minutes before breakfast,
after lunch, or after dinner.
Over the 24 hours
they exercised in the evening,
432 calories were burned off.
On the afternoon exercise day,
they burned off
446 calories of fat.
They also had a control day
with no exercise at all,
and on that day, they burned
through 456 fat calories.
That’s disappointing—it’s like
they never walked at all.
But the same amount
of exercise before breakfast
resulted in 717 calories
of fat loss.
Over the course of a day
timing matters,
so much so that when it
comes to an hour of walking,
exercise increases 24-hour
fat burning only
when it is performed
before breakfast.
Here’s the fat balance
graph with no exercise.
You can see the fat storage bump up
at breakfast, lunch, and supper,
before slowly coming
back down overnight.
Exercise in the afternoon
or evening
and end up with more fat
than not exercising at all,
but exercise in the morning
and at least
your fat balance comes
back to baseline.
All such similar studies
on both men and women
show we burn through more fat
on the days we exercise before,
rather than after eating.
After reading the
chronobiology chapter though
or watching my
chronobiology videos,
an alternative explanation
may spring to mind.
Maybe it’s just a morning thing.
Maybe it has nothing
to do with meals,
and your circadian rhythm
is just dictating the difference.
No. Exercising in the morning
after breakfast
appears no better than exercising
in the evening after dinner,
and exercising before
breakfast works better
than immediately after breakfast,
both still in the morning.
It really does seem to be
a pre- versus post-meal effect.
But why?
Carbohydrate is the preferred
fuel of the body.
When you eat sugars or starches,
they get broken down
and converted into blood sugar.
After a meal, blood sugars rise
and your muscles are quick
to snatch it up for fuel
without having to rely
much on your energy stores.
If you instead take a siesta,
and your muscles have
no immediate need for energy,
the excess blood sugar from a meal
can be stored in our
muscles in the form
of glycogen for later use.
Glycogen is just a bunch
of blood sugar molecules
strung together into
a mass of branches
that can be broken off and used
for quick bursts of energy
any time we need them.
If you exercise after a meal,
your muscles can siphon off
some of the extra blood sugar
floating around for energy.
Before a meal, your
muscles have to instead
resort to dipping
into your energy stores
and end up burning mostly
a combination
of glycogen and fat.
That explains why you burn
more fat during fasted exercise,
but what about all the extra fat
burned throughout
the rest of the day?
Glycogen is more than a store.
Glycogen isn’t just
an energy reserve,
but acts as a sensor capable
of activating metabolic pathways.
Exercising before
breakfast can exhaust
as much as 18 percent
of your glycogen stores,
and that depletion can
act as a powerful rallying cry
to your fatty tissues
to start pulling
more of their own weight
by breaking down more fat.
The lower glycogen
stores fall,
the greater the sustained
24-hour fat loss.
How long do you have
to go without food
in order to trigger this effect?
Six hours may be sufficient;
so, it doesn’t have
to be before breakfast.
If you timed it right, you could
exercise before a late lunch,
or if you have an early enough
lunch, maybe before dinner
when you get home from work.
If exercise in a fasted
state isn’t possible,
does it matter what you eat?
Insulin release after a meal
appears to play a critical role
in suppressing fat breakdown,
explaining why lower
glycemic foods—
in this case, muesli
versus cornflakes—
can have less of an effect.
Lentils were identified
as a promising option
for maintaining
athletic endurance
(which can take a hit
on an empty stomach)
while maintaining more
of the fat dissolution.
Lentils are said to be
unlikely to be consumed
by the general population
due to 'low palatability".
They obviously haven’t tried
my mom’s lentil soup.
It's worth mentioning
that although
there’s increased 24-hour
fat burning exercising
in a fasted state,
the only way to see
if this facilitates
weight loss over time
is to put it to the test,
which we’ll explore next.